Finding aid to the Gay Nurses Alliance records SSC.MS.00732
Sophia Smith Collection
Gay Nurses Alliance records
1971-1984
Sophia Smith Collection
Gay Nurses Alliance
SSC.MS.00732
2 linear feet (1 legal document box, 1 half legal document box, 1 flat oversize box, and 2 boxes.)
The collection contains photographs and recordings of conferences and presentations, articles and publications on gays and gays in health care, and of newsletters, mailings, and fliers. Also included are the working papers of the Gay Nurse Alliance, an advocacy group for gay patients and nurses and an education disseminator for health care professionals and others.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was gifted by E. Carolyn Innes in 2014 and 2016. Additional materials were received in 2018.
Biographical Note
E. Carolyn Innes and G. David Waldron co-founded the Gay Nurses'Alliance (GNA) in Philadelphia, PA, in August 1973 to advocate for gay patients and nurses and educate health care professionals and others. Encouraged by her mentor Barbara Gittings, Innes approached Waldron with the idea of establishing a gay caucus within the American Nurses Association. While the plan didn't evolve exactly that way, Innes, Waldron, their partners, and one other nurse, began to organize an independent Alliance. In October of 1973 they gave the presentation"Gay People/Straight Health Care" at the Pennsylvania Nurses Association conference. Though they were not officially recognized by the Association or conference, response to the talk was so positive that they repeated it to another packed room the following morning. Chapters of GNA were established in Boston, MA and New York City, NY. Chapter membership fees, combined with personal funds, enabled Innes and Waldron to attend the American Nurses Association Convention in San Francisco. They also began doing numerous speaking engagements, utilizing a slide show created by member Jeri Dilno Was the photographer and graphic designer for the GNA newsletter THE SIGNAL and the designer of the GNA button. Other key members included Tony Amadeo who was the head of the Pennsylvania caucus and Bob Simco was GNA's business manager, In 1977 GNA had its first annual conference. Though the organization continued to grow, by 1978 lack of member involvement prompted John C. Lawrence, president and National Coordinator East, and Bob Miller, secretary of the Alliance, to consider disbanding unless others stepped forward. By the early 1980s the Alliance was defunct.
Other Finding Aids
The collection has container lists that are available upon request by contacting specialcollections@smith.edu
Related Materials
Documenting Lesbian Lives Oral History Project
Scope and Contents
The bulk consists of photographs and recordings of conferences and presentations, articles and publications on gays and gays in health care, and of newsletters, mailings, and fliers. There are some manuscripts, correspondence, and other publicity material from GNA and other organizations, including GNA's Signal newsletter. Also includes buttons and badges from conferences.
Gay rights -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Gays -- Health and hygiene; Nurses -- United States -- History -- Sources; Health care reform -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Hospitals -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Nurses -- History -- Sources; articles; Audiotapes; correspondence; Fliers; Manuscripts; Newspapers; Pamphlets; photographs; Programs; Publicity; Publications; Gay Nurses Alliance; Innes, E. Carolyn; Innes, E. Carolyn; Waldron, David
- David Waldron collection of Gay Nurses Alliance records, 2018-S-0075; 1.25 linear feet (1 legal document box, 1 half legal document box, 1 flat oversize box); 2 items (2 audiocassettes)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes organizational information on the Gay Nurses' Alliance (pamphlets, newsletters and drafts, mission statement letters, and publicity), as well as conference information and correspondence, legal information, and essays. Also includes buttons, badges, news clippings, and correspondence with relevant organizations, individual organizers, and supportive people nationwide.
  - Signal newsletter and drafts, 1975-1984; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Gay Nurses' Alliance brochures, mission statement letters, letterhead, and other organization materials, 1973-1975; 4 folders (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - Press releases, publicity reports, and requests for information, 1973-1975; 3 folders (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - American Nurses' Association information and resolutions, 1973-1974, 1978; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Personal materials of David Waldron and Carolyn Innes, 1972; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Speakers' bureau information and correspondence, 1974; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - American Nurses' Association Commission on Human Rights, 1974-1979; 3 folders (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Philadelphia Nurses' Association conventions, 1973-1975; 3 folders (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Writings on homophobia and gay rights, 1974-1984; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - News publications for conferences, organizations, 1974-1984; 6 items (6 papers) (Box 3)
  - Correspondence between the Gay Nurses' Alliance and other organizations and individuals, 1973-1982; 11 folders (11 folders) (Box 2)
  - Massachusetts Nurses Association tape, 1975 January 23; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 1)
  - American Nurses' Association Convention tape: AIDS, 1984; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 1)
  - Loving Women, Loving Men: Gay Liberation and the Church by Sally Gearhart and William R. Johnson, inscribed by Johnson to the GNA, 1974; 1 items (1 book) (Box 1)
  - Photographs, Boston conference, 1974; 2 folders (2 envelopes) (Box 2)
  - Photographs, San Francisco conference, 1974 June; 1 folders (1 envelope) (Box 2)
  - David Waldron's conference badges, approximately 1974-1984; 1 folders (1 envelope) (Box 2)
  - Buttons, various causes, approximately 1974-1984; 6 folders (6 envelopes) (Box 2)